there was one
Uma nikaya 128
buckaleza
and he he basically
he signed into these Pickers and he asks
them if we've attained any super even State
if we've attained any super even State
and meditation
and they talk about perception of light
and vision of forms arising and then
going away and they don't know why and
then he talks about doubt
excitement desire for more of a
hindrances hindrances basically so
just wanted some clarification on the uh
the perception of light
the forms aspect of it like
does that refer to exactly well
see the Buddha gave the answer there
the Buddha gave the answer there
by
telling them they need to overcome the
hindrances
see if you want to understand it you
have to be free from hindrances
otherwise whatever answers given
you'll be doubtful about it but then you
won't see that because you think oh
that's what it is
so um
just if you need to wrap your head
around it but don't take it as an answer
answer or that's what perception of
light is because it isn't it is when you
see it for what it is
but if you need to wrap your head around
it but not confuse it for an answer
well even take it on a most mundane
level a phenomenon of light
phenomenon of presence phenomenon of
non-dark brightness brightness yeah any epithet
brightness brightness yeah any epithet
you can give it
and that is really such
usually when minds are just um
when minds are just um
on average drenched with sensuality and
so on all these things are kind of
abstract or mystical
but if the Mind dries up
then you could actually just determine
to be precipient upright
specifically in the same sense you could
determine to be precipient of Infinite
Space or um yeah signless
or um yeah signless
development of a mind turn away from
picking on any limiter
which is us
but like yeah you know I had before people
like yeah you know I had before people
ask where are you going to understand
the first John and then this is in the
second John and this is the first round
poor John I don't quite get this aspect
could you clarify it's like so are you
saying you have developed the three
genres in which case you wouldn't be
asking about the fourth because it's the
same principle
but it's like no it's just this
information that I wrap my head around
that it's satisfying for me
because I think now that's vaginas are
and that's okay but they're not
even himself describes to the utmost
detail about the perception of light or
what third genre is it isn't for as long
as you don't see it
so the danger is obviously not like also
I shouldn't learn or get information but
I should be very careful to not conflate
it with the actual development of that
thing so that's exactly see for as long
as they are doubtful they couldn't quite
understand it why how and all the other
kind of uh more particular permutations
in regard to the phenomenon of light
and but if they're free from that if the
mind has been freed from hindrances
and that's where you put the emphasis on
not on clarifying this which I would
like to know
then you get to know it
so
why would you think it's relevant the
perception of light what would you
expect from it in terms of meditation
or was it just started kind of wrap my
head around it
it was just
um
so I I actually wrote notes down about
it like okay what is this perception of
light refer to I looked at the poly it's
like understanding that brings this sort of
understanding that brings this sort of
light
phenomena of late this uh
brightness understanding clarity
in things
um is how I took it but it was so I
think the translation of
or like you see something in meditation
oh you see this light this physical
forms yeah well mind you most of the
most of the
instructions that I heard
it's on the level of like even nimited
that way as he's
mystical things that you kind of kind of
just see in your meditation or limit as
your significant to the signs and
features that you you do see day to day
level on the most course to the most
it's the same thing yeah
um
so yeah it's most certainly not the
perception of light or some Source or
something the the way people would uh
can just be read so like in that form in
that way it's it's on the level like the
reason why the Buddha did talk about
that or the other kind of
seemingly mystical sounding properties
it's because
um
when you practice that mind turning away
from things in in Jannah in first John
in the second John in the third genre
these things are the um
the properties the the the uh the
aspects that one
that one
could then
um kind of uh use and also to discern
that turning away
of the Mind
in other words for example
Turning Away of cheetah when turns away
from vitakovichara in the first genre as
in when it surmounts it when it is not
hindered by movements of itakovichara
is light
is uh signless
is
you could you could describe it even in
some idiosyncratic ways if you want
but it would have been the Buddha the
idiosyncratic weights were the most
accurate ways
so now
say you're not in the first genre
distractions got in the way or you
haven't quite fully understood and so on
but you now can use those properties
that you have experienced on a kind of
mind semante with Chara to restart the
practice to re-establish the mind in the
same way so establish upon that
perception of light it doesn't work for
anyone or everyone because not everyone
would experience it the same way but
there are certain Universal
characteristics of mind turning away from the domain
of mind turning away from the domain
that he just surmounted
but again from this point of view you
could see that it's nothing mystical
about it it's it's and you could even as
I said you could take even some
mundane experience of peace or a calm
mind and if you were to really look for
the universal
description they were kind of always
Encompass that experience you would find
probably relatively similar terms that
then if you are skilled in training your
mind would be enough
to re-establish the direction of that oh
and that's the whole like Sati patana
panasati let me keep like knowing the
mind he experienced I actually
experienced the mind like this I should
experience like that I will be
liberating the Mind liberating the mind
he breeds in liberating the mind he
breathes out so you start already
uh Discerning a relationship with that
mind and how to communicate to it so to
speak and then I will make my breathing
in I'll make this mine light
I'll make this mind weightless I'll make
this Mighty measurable
all the properties you would find I'll
make this mind completely uh
turn away from any slightest signs and
features I will protect I will cultivate that
I will protect I will cultivate that
animita meditation
um but even like in the suit is like
what we recently came across those
verses that we mentioned in
hitting one of the previous talks about
that nun
like it's usually commonly translated
like oh I meditated on uh on the
signlessness or something he doesn't
actually say that
he just says
yes so I was cultivating signlessness
now sure yeah cultivation in meditation
well does it does cultivation mean what
you take meditation to mean it can if we
qualify it but when you say meditation
we all know what that means I mean
sitting cross-light watching tip of my
nose or something of that kind technique
technique of of silenceness kamatan that
Arjun gave me he's like no she turned
her mind away from signs and features
there will be otherwise con inducing a
velocity version of Egypt and she
protected that she cultivated that until
the mind was fully released from going
back to things that are now understood
as unownable as perilous danger as not
worth the passion and so on
so yes she meditated on it
but not in that in that common sense but
if you just carelessly use this one
meditate my meditation and so on it
becomes okay so it's some sort of
these limiters and these lights and
these properties they would come on a
kind of understanding
understanding this passion understanding
how to turn your mind away from things
that are unsuitable will become this
kind of extension of this mystical kind
of expectations
and then I had this light I don't quite
know what it means it Bears no relevance
to my liability to suffer but it was
super special so must have been Jana
and it's a kind of very different
picture that you would get reading the
suitors as to you know what genres would
result in and lead to and
turning away from sensuality and being
unable to be hindered by any of the five
hindrances there is already certain uh like when it
there is already certain uh like when it
comes to Consciousness there is already
a certain like uh just Radiance to being
aware it doesn't matter what it is
presence of something presence of
something to that extent it's lit up to
that extent that's describe some of the
descriptions of Consciousness which one
well it is radiant or bright and
so on its own again people tend to
mystify that term or Consciousness is
always pure and bright and eternal and
everything no no literally means
property of that aggregate is such to be
bright and luminous all around and not
necessarily Bound By Any subject or
perception of ownership
because as he said in many times before
you know the suit is like the upadhana
the Assumption the craving is not part
of the Aggregates it's not any of the
Aggregates it's not in them
but it's not to be found anywhere else
except where the five Aggregates are
oh so it's neither here nor there so to
speak but it's with them
says what is why why is it like that
well desire and lust in regards to the
father grids upadhana is there
but five Aggregates as I said in you
know my old essays they they completely
unaware of you unaware of your ownership
and aware of everything you're going
through unaware of each other it's just
five heaps that's why they're called
candas means heaps of stuff separate from one
means heaps of stuff separate from one
another
and property of the Heap of
Consciousness is a brightness lightness
Luminosity whatever else on its own now
sure as we just discussed this I can
mystify that because I wrap my head
around the idea
but one thing is to think it another
thing is to actually see it for yourself
so and is that uh what you your original
question about that so the monks
couldn't quite get this perception of
light oh because they were not free from
doubt they were still accessing it
through their abstract Notions of it and
thus becoming liable to that
they haven't developed Minds
sufficiently and one who does develop the mind
and one who does develop the mind
sufficiently you just find that
Consciousness luminous all around that
is equally impermanent like the form
like the feeling like the perception
like cincottas
there's nothing special to it but yes if
your mind has been trained and developed
and be drawn from the senses you can use
the property of that light Luminosity to
remove any traces
of ownership and obstruction so to speak
but if you haven't developed your mind
but like the idea
of luminous unpolluted
and then just take it in a mystical
Direction then you feel Exempted from
everything else because you explained
your experience well but see there's
always light Consciousness is eternal
it's pure it cannot be polluted
yes for somebody who is now in other
hunt but do you start from that position
if so the Buddha would have just said
listen monks the Aggregates cannot be
polluted go home now
we're done here
the whole gradual training withdrawal
taming enduring that Kanti the whole
thing and then sure when you see the
and then sure when you see the
Luminosity of Consciousness or that as
he described in that casino suit that
says yeah it's the most refined of all
casinos um but even that the target understood
um but even that the target understood
the gratification the danger the escape
in regard to the totality of
consciousness and even such a pure refined thing oh no
and even such a pure refined thing oh no
even that it's not worth holding but
Hearing delighting in finding the safety
in and that's what people who who kind
of you know have some sort of underlying
either advice and on Duality View
cannot understand
in the sense that they cannot understand
that that's the difference that the
Buddha was teaching
it's not that he was teaching something
else no he should take whatever
concept idea sense of release you have
found and you choose basically deep down to
and you choose basically deep down to
regard it as safe
as friendly
as a My Shelter
as my help as my reference point
and the whole point is you could equally
choose to not regard itself
but people don't choose that because
that's too unpleasant
so people always say oh well look you
know it's love and light it's your true
being it's your intrinsic self
because see you know when you experience
these things they you know they just
happen like that it's like oh yeah that
is true and when you experience
suffering and pain that's also your
intrinsic being otherwise why would you
experience it in the first place it's on
the same level
so you can't pick and choose
and that's exactly what a Buddha said if
the life human life were only suffering
people would not be enamored with form
and sensuality and everything else
if it were only pleasure well people
would not seek the way out
so you know I'm liable to both and
that's not a good deal for somebody who
understands the Buddhist teaching so
even the most refined
concept idea sense of safety experience
meditation release
you could
if you understood the value of the
Buddhist teaching you could see oh even
that is not worth
taking his mind for me I am my safety my
shelter even that has to be subjected to
the same Anita that these cause things
are and that's when the Mind turns away
and experience this passion and so on
but that's now on the level of much
deeper View because you can keep saying
that to yourself as a mantra or this is
all a niche it's only it's a deep down
is your mind very much sort of gripped
with the joy towards the the non-dual
experience of of universe you had
or is your mind truly able to oh this is
dangerous and feel that Peril of even
that and
and
I mean he was teaching that in many
different guys but he was saying for
Jannah like when everything is factually
like when everything is factually
wholesome in it the experience there are
no underlying Tendencies there uh no
craving you know no hindrances it says
and then I tell monks now monk regard
that as that as a DOT as a Peril as debt
as unsuitable as harmful so the mind
will turn away from it and then you will
know it's fully liberated nothing
absolutely nothing is worth clinging to
welcoming Delight again
and that is very frightening for for
somebody who has uh whose mind is not
been developed and that's exactly when
people who are not quite prepared
already went to todubura insisted on
certain questions he answered them
explain what nibana is and they just
fell on the ground pulling their hair
with that description in complete
basically anxiety saying well that that
will kill me that will destroy me there
will be no no me after that that's
no Eternal safety coming from this but
again it is eternal safety so to speak
if you truly give up any need for safety
and you will give up any need for safety
if you give up the slightest traces of
ownership of any phenomenon
but somebody who has not done that and
tries to perceive giving it all up its
equals Death basically from their point
of view equals what death is
and that's that difference it's not like
in Buddhism you find another thing
nibana is just on the level of these
other perceptions of light and higher
self and Cosmos or whatever you might
find you're sheltered in no no no no no
it's like nothing is worth clinging to
so whatever experience you have fine
doesn't matter it's real as such
it's perilous it's dangerous you need to
understand the extent of gratification
the danger and the Escape
in order to truly experience what the
Buddha was teaching so it's not a
replacement it's a complete abandonment